<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PyPy (Posts about cpyext)</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.pypy.org/categories/cpyext.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2026 &lt;a href="mailto:pypy-dev@pypy.org"&gt;The PyPy Team&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 00:22:36 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Leysin 2020 Sprint Report</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/03/leysin-2020-sprint-report-764567777353955897.html</link><dc:creator>hodgestar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;At the end of February ten of us gathered in Leysin, Switzerland to work on&lt;br&gt;
a variety of topics including &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/pyhandle/hpy/"&gt;HPy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://buildbot.pypy.org/summary?branch=py3.7"&gt;PyPy Python 3.7&lt;/a&gt; support and the PyPy&lt;br&gt;
migration to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/"&gt;Heptapod&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PIs_hVhn3RY/XnFDceuihNI/AAAAAAAAbRg/LKMOMWxeFw4jhcwqy8jx7iKzKE01fbfxQCEwYBhgL/s1600/2020_leysin_sprint_attendees.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="180" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PIs_hVhn3RY/XnFDceuihNI/AAAAAAAAbRg/LKMOMWxeFw4jhcwqy8jx7iKzKE01fbfxQCEwYBhgL/s320/2020_leysin_sprint_attendees.jpg" width="320"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
We had a fun and productive week. The snow was beautiful. There was skiing&lt;br&gt;
and lunch at the top of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berneuse"&gt;Berneuse&lt;/a&gt;, cooking together, some late nights at&lt;br&gt;
the pub next door, some even later nights coding, and of course the&lt;br&gt;
obligatory cheese fondue outing.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
There were a few of us participating in a PyPy sprint for the first time&lt;br&gt;
and a few familiar faces who had attended many sprints. Many different&lt;br&gt;
projects were represented including PyPy, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/pyhandle/hpy/"&gt;HPy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/graalvm/graalpython"&gt;GraalPython&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/"&gt;Heptapod&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dgrunwald/rust-cpython"&gt;rust-cpython&lt;/a&gt;. The atmosphere was relaxed and welcoming, so if&lt;br&gt;
you're thinking of attending the next one -- please do!&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Topics worked on:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
HPy&lt;/h2&gt;
HPy is a new project to design and implement a better API for extending&lt;br&gt;
Python in C. If you're unfamiliar with it you can read more about it at&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/pyhandle/hpy/"&gt;HPy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
A lot of attention was devoted to the Big HPy Design Discussion which&lt;br&gt;
took up two full mornings. So much was decided that this will likely&lt;br&gt;
get its own detailed write-up, but bigger topics included:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the HPy GetAttr, SetAttr, GetItem and SetItem methods,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HPy_FromVoidP and HPy_AsVoidP for passing HPy handles to C functions&lt;br&gt;
that pass void* pointers to callbacks,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoiding having va_args as part of the ABI,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exception handling,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;support for creating custom types.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Quite a few things got worked on too:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;implemented support for writing methods that take keyword arguments with&lt;br&gt;
HPy_METH_KEYWORDS,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;implemented HPy_GetAttr, HPy_SetAttr, HPy_GetItem, and HPy_SetItem,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;started implementing support for adding custom types,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;started implementing dumping JSON objects in ultrajson-hpy,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;refactored the PyPy GIL to improve the interaction between HPy and&lt;br&gt;
PyPy's cpyext,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;experimented with adding HPy support to rust-cpython.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
And there was some discussion of the next steps of the HPy initiative&lt;br&gt;
including writing documentation, setting up websites and funding, and&lt;br&gt;
possibly organising another HPy gathering later in the year.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
PyPy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Georges gave a presentation on the Heptapod topic and branch workflows&lt;br&gt;
and showed everyone how to use hg-evolve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work was done on improving the PyPy CI buildbot post the move to&lt;br&gt;
heptapod, including a light-weight pre-merge CI and restricting&lt;br&gt;
when the full CI is run to only branch commits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of work was done improving the -D tests. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Armin demoed VRSketch and NaN Industries in VR, including an implementation&lt;br&gt;
of the Game of Life within NaN Industries!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skiing!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
Immediately after the sprint large parts of Europe and the world were&lt;br&gt;
hit by the COVID-19 epidemic. It was good to spend time together before&lt;br&gt;
travelling ceased to be a sensible idea and many gatherings were cancelled.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Keep safe out there everyone.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The HPy &amp;amp; PyPy Team &amp;amp; Friends&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;In joke for those who attended the sprint: Please don't replace this blog post&lt;br&gt;
with its Swedish translation (or indeed a translation to any other language :).&lt;/i&gt;</description><category>cpyext</category><category>CPython</category><category>GraalPython</category><category>Heptapod</category><category>hpy</category><category>pypy</category><category>pypy3</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/03/leysin-2020-sprint-report-764567777353955897.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2020 21:57:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Inside cpyext: Why emulating CPython C API is so Hard</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2018/09/inside-cpyext-why-emulating-cpython-c-8083064623681286567.html</link><dc:creator>Antonio Cuni</dc:creator><description>&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div class="document" id="inside-cpyext-why-emulating-cpython-c-api-is-so-hard"&gt;
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; is PyPy's subsystem which provides a compatibility
layer to compile and run CPython C extensions inside PyPy.  Often people ask
why a particular C extension doesn't work or is very slow on PyPy.
Usually it is hard to answer without going into technical details. The goal of
this blog post is to explain some of these technical details, so that we can
simply link here instead of explaining again and again :).&lt;br&gt;
From a 10.000 foot view, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; is PyPy's version of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;"Python.h"&lt;/tt&gt;. Every time
you compile an extension which uses that header file, you are using &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt;.
This includes extension explicitly written in C (such as &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;numpy&lt;/tt&gt;) and
extensions which are generated from other compilers/preprocessors
(e.g. &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Cython&lt;/tt&gt;).&lt;br&gt;
At the time of writing, the current status is that most C extensions "just
work". Generally speaking, you can simply &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;pip install&lt;/tt&gt; them,
provided they use the public, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/index.html"&gt;official C API&lt;/a&gt; instead of poking at private
implementation details.  However, the performance of cpyext is generally
poor. A Python program which makes heavy use of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; extensions
is likely to be slower on PyPy than on CPython.&lt;br&gt;
Note: in this blog post we are talking about Python 2.7 because it is still
the default version of PyPy: however most of the implementation of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; is
shared with PyPy3, so everything applies to that as well.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="c-api-overview"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
C API Overview&lt;/h1&gt;
In CPython, which is written in C, Python objects are represented as &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;,
i.e. (mostly) opaque pointers to some common "base struct".&lt;br&gt;
CPython uses a very simple memory management scheme: when you create an
object, you allocate a block of memory of the appropriate size on the heap.
Depending on the details, you might end up calling different allocators, but
for the sake of simplicity, you can think that this ends up being a call to
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;malloc()&lt;/tt&gt;. The resulting block of memory is initialized and casted to to
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;: this address never changes during the object lifetime, and the
C code can freely pass it around, store it inside containers, retrieve it
later, etc.&lt;br&gt;
Memory is managed using reference counting. When you create a new reference to
an object, or you discard a reference you own, you have to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/refcounting.html#c.Py_INCREF"&gt;increment&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/refcounting.html#c.Py_DECREF"&gt;decrement&lt;/a&gt; the reference counter accordingly. When the reference counter goes to
0, it means that the object is no longer used and can safely be
destroyed. Again, we can simplify and say that this results in a call to
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;free()&lt;/tt&gt;, which finally releases the memory which was allocated by &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;malloc()&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Generally speaking, the only way to operate on a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; is to call the
appropriate API functions. For example, to convert a given &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; to a C
integer, you can use &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/int.html#c.PyInt_AsLong"&gt;PyInt_AsLong()&lt;/a&gt;; to add two objects together, you can
call &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/number.html#c.PyNumber_Add"&gt;PyNumber_Add()&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Internally, PyPy uses a similar approach. All Python objects are subclasses of
the RPython &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; class, and they are operated by calling methods on the
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;space&lt;/tt&gt; singleton, which represents the interpreter.&lt;br&gt;
At first, it looks very easy to write a compatibility layer: just make
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; an alias for &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt;, and write simple RPython functions
(which will be translated to C by the RPython compiler) which call the
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;space&lt;/tt&gt; accordingly:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;pre class="code python literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="keyword"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name function"&gt;PyInt_AsLong&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;space&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;o&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="keyword"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;space&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="operator"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;int_w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;o&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="keyword"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name function"&gt;PyNumber_Add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;space&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;o1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;o2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="keyword"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;space&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="operator"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;o1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;o2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
Actually, the code above is not too far from the real
implementation. However, there are tons of gory details which make it much
harder than it looks, and much slower unless you pay a lot of attention
to performance.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-pypy-gc"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
The PyPy GC&lt;/h1&gt;
To understand some of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; challenges, you need to have at least a rough
idea of how the PyPy GC works.&lt;br&gt;
Contrarily to the popular belief, the "Garbage Collector" is not only about
collecting garbage: instead, it is generally responsible for all memory
management, including allocation and deallocation.&lt;br&gt;
Whereas CPython uses a combination of malloc/free/refcounting to manage
memory, the PyPy GC uses a completely different approach. It is designed
assuming that a dynamic language like Python behaves the following way:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You create, either directly or indirectly, lots of objects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of these objects are temporary and very short-lived. Think e.g. of
doing &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;a + b + c&lt;/tt&gt;: you need to allocate an object to hold the temporary
result of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;a + b&lt;/tt&gt;, then it dies very quickly because you no longer need it
when you do the final &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;+ c&lt;/tt&gt; part.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only small fraction of the objects survive and stay around for a while.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
So, the strategy is: make allocation as fast as possible; make deallocation of
short-lived objects as fast as possible; find a way to handle the remaining
small set of objects which actually survive long enough to be important.&lt;br&gt;
This is done using a &lt;strong&gt;Generational GC&lt;/strong&gt;: the basic idea is the following:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a nursery, where we allocate "young objects" very quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the nursery is full, we start what we call a "minor collection".&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We do a quick scan to determine the small set of objects which survived so
far&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We &lt;strong&gt;move&lt;/strong&gt; these objects out of the nursery, and we place them in the
area of memory which contains the "old objects". Since the address of the
objects changes, we fix all the references to them accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple" start="4"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;now the nursery contains only objects which "died young". We can
discard all of them very quickly, reset the nursery, and use the same area
of memory to allocate new objects from now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In practice, this scheme works very well and it is one of the reasons why PyPy
is much faster than CPython.  However, careful readers have surely noticed
that this is a problem for &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt;. On one hand, we have PyPy objects which
can potentially move and change their underlying memory address; on the other
hand, we need a way to represent them as fixed-address &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; when we
pass them to C extensions.  We surely need a way to handle that.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pyobject-in-pypy"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; in PyPy&lt;/h1&gt;
Another challenge is that sometimes, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; structs are not completely
opaque: there are parts of the public API which expose to the user specific
fields of some concrete C struct. For example the definition of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/typeobj.html"&gt;PyTypeObject&lt;/a&gt;
which exposes many of the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;tp_*&lt;/tt&gt; slots to the user.
Since the low-level layout of PyPy &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; objects is completely different
than the one used by CPython, we cannot simply pass RPython objects to C; we
need a way to handle the difference.&lt;br&gt;
So, we have two issues so far: objects can move, and incompatible
low-level layouts. &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; solves both by decoupling the RPython and the C
representations. We have two "views" of the same entity, depending on whether
we are in the PyPy world (the movable &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; subclass) or in the C world
(the non-movable &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;).&lt;br&gt;
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; are created lazily, only when they are actually needed. The
vast majority of PyPy objects are never passed to any C extension, so we don't
pay any penalty in that case. However, the first time we pass a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; to
C, we allocate and initialize its &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; counterpart.&lt;br&gt;
The same idea applies also to objects which are created in C, e.g. by calling
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/allocation.html#c.PyObject_New"&gt;PyObject_New()&lt;/a&gt;. At first, only the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; exists and it is
exclusively managed by reference counting. As soon as we pass it to the PyPy
world (e.g. as a return value of a function call), we create its &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt;
counterpart, which is managed by the GC as usual.&lt;br&gt;
Here we start to see why calling cpyext modules is more costly in PyPy than in
CPython. We need to pay some penalty for all the conversions between
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Moreover, the first time we pass a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; to C we also need to allocate
the memory for the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; using a slowish "CPython-style" memory
allocator. In practice, for all the objects which are passed to C we pay more
or less the same costs as CPython, thus effectively "undoing" the speedup
guaranteed by PyPy's Generational GC under normal circumstances.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="maintaining-the-link-between-w-root-and-pyobject"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
Maintaining the link between &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
We now need a way to convert between &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; and
vice-versa; also, we need to to ensure that the lifetime of the two entities
are in sync. In particular:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as long as the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; is kept alive by the GC, we want the
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; to live even if its refcount drops to 0;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as long as the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; has a refcount greater than 0, we want to
make sure that the GC does not collect the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; ⇨ &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; link is maintained by the special field
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/tree/branch/py3.6/pypy/module/cpyext/parse/cpyext_object.h#lines-5"&gt;ob_pypy_link&lt;/a&gt; which is added to all &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;. On a 64 bit machine this
means that all &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; have 8 bytes of overhead, but then the
conversion is very quick, just reading the field.&lt;br&gt;
For the other direction, we generally don't want to do the same: the
assumption is that the vast majority of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; objects will never be
passed to C, and adding an overhead of 8 bytes to all of them is a
waste. Instead, in the general case the link is maintained by using a
dictionary, where &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; are the keys and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; the values.&lt;br&gt;
However, for a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/tree/branch/py3.6/pypy/module/cpyext/pyobject.py#lines-66"&gt;few selected&lt;/a&gt; &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; subclasses we &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; maintain a
direct link using the special &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;_cpy_ref&lt;/tt&gt; field to improve performance. In
particular, we use it for &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_TypeObject&lt;/tt&gt; (which is big anyway, so a 8 bytes
overhead is negligible) and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_NoneObject&lt;/tt&gt;. &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;None&lt;/tt&gt; is passed around very
often, so we want to ensure that the conversion to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; is very
fast. Moreover it's a singleton, so the 8 bytes overhead is negligible as
well.&lt;br&gt;
This means that in theory, passing an arbitrary Python object to C is
potentially costly, because it involves doing a dictionary lookup.  We assume
that this cost will eventually show up in the profiler: however, at the time
of writing there are other parts of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; which are even more costly (as we
will show later), so the cost of the dict lookup is never evident in the
profiler.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="crossing-the-border-between-rpython-and-c"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
Crossing the border between RPython and C&lt;/h1&gt;
There are two other things we need to care about whenever we cross the border
between RPython and C, and vice-versa: exception handling and the GIL.&lt;br&gt;
In the C API, exceptions are raised by calling &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/exceptions.html#c.PyErr_SetString"&gt;PyErr_SetString()&lt;/a&gt; (or one of
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/exceptions.html#exception-handling"&gt;many other functions&lt;/a&gt; which have a similar effect), which basically works by
creating an exception value and storing it in some global variable. The
function then signals that an exception has occurred by returning an error value,
usually &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;NULL&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
On the other hand, in the PyPy interpreter, exceptions are propagated by raising the
RPython-level &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/tree/branch/py3.6/pypy/interpreter/error.py#lines-20"&gt;OperationError&lt;/a&gt; exception, which wraps the actual app-level
exception values. To harmonize the two worlds, whenever we return from C to
RPython, we need to check whether a C API exception was raised and if so turn it
into an &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;OperationError&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
We won't dig into details of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/tree/branch/py3.6/pypy/module/cpyext/api.py#lines-205"&gt;how the GIL is handled in cpyext&lt;/a&gt;.
For the purpose of this post, it is enough to know that whenever we enter
C land, we store the current thread id into a global variable which is
accessible also from C; conversely, whenever we go back from RPython to C, we
restore this value to 0.&lt;br&gt;
Similarly, we need to do the inverse operations whenever you need to cross the
border between C and RPython, e.g. by calling a Python callback from C code.&lt;br&gt;
All this complexity is automatically handled by the RPython function
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/tree/branch/py3.6/pypy/module/cpyext/api.py#lines-1757"&gt;generic_cpy_call&lt;/a&gt;. If you look at the code you see that it takes care of 4
things:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handling the GIL as explained above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handling exceptions, if they are raised.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Converting arguments from &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Converting the return value from &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
So, we can see that calling C from RPython introduce some overhead.
Can we measure it?&lt;br&gt;
Assuming that the conversion between &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; has a
reasonable cost (as explained by the previous section), the overhead
introduced by a single border-cross is still acceptable, especially if the
callee is doing some non-negligible amount of work.&lt;br&gt;
However this is not always the case. There are basically three problems that
make (or used to make) &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; super slow:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paying the border-crossing cost for trivial operations which are called
very often, such as &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Py_INCREF&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crossing the border back and forth many times, even if it's not strictly
needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paying an excessive cost for argument and return value conversions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The next sections explain in more detail each of these problems.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="avoiding-unnecessary-roundtrips"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
Avoiding unnecessary roundtrips&lt;/h1&gt;
Prior to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pypy.org/posts/2017/10/cape-of-good-hope-for-pypy-hello-from-3656631725712879033.html"&gt;2017 Cape Town Sprint&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; was horribly slow, and we were
well aware of it: the main reason was that we never really paid too much
attention to performance. As explained in the blog post, emulating all the
CPython quirks is basically a nightmare, so better to concentrate on
correctness first.&lt;br&gt;
However, we didn't really know &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; it was so slow. We had theories and
assumptions, usually pointing at the cost of conversions between &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt;
and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;, but we never actually measured it.&lt;br&gt;
So, we decided to write a set of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/antocuni/cpyext-benchmarks"&gt;cpyext microbenchmarks&lt;/a&gt; to measure the
performance of various operations.  The result was somewhat surprising: the
theory suggests that when you do a cpyext C call, you should pay the
border-crossing costs only once, but what the profiler told us was that we
were paying the cost of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;generic_cpy_call&lt;/tt&gt; several times more than what we expected.&lt;br&gt;
After a bit of investigation, we discovered this was ultimately caused by our
"correctness-first" approach. For simplicity of development and testing, when
we started &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; we wrote everything in RPython: thus, every single API call
made from C (like the omnipresent &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/arg.html#c.PyArg_ParseTuple"&gt;PyArg_ParseTuple()&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/int.html#c.PyInt_AsLong"&gt;PyInt_AsLong()&lt;/a&gt;, etc.)
had to cross back the C-to-RPython border. This was especially daunting for
very simple and frequent operations like &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Py_INCREF&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Py_DECREF&lt;/tt&gt;,
which CPython implements as a single assembly instruction!&lt;br&gt;
Another source of slow down was the implementation of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyTypeObject&lt;/tt&gt; slots.
At the C level, these are function pointers which the interpreter calls to do
certain operations, e.g. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/typeobj.html#c.PyTypeObject.tp_new"&gt;tp_new&lt;/a&gt; to allocate a new instance of that type.&lt;br&gt;
As usual, we have some magic to implement slots in RPython; in particular,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/tree/branch/py3.6/pypy/module/cpyext/api.py#lines-362"&gt;_make_wrapper&lt;/a&gt; does the opposite of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;generic_cpy_call&lt;/tt&gt;: it takes a
RPython function and wraps it into a C function which can be safely called
from C, handling the GIL, exceptions and argument conversions automatically.&lt;br&gt;
This was very handy during the development of cpyext, but it might result in
some bad nonsense; consider what happens when you call the following C
function:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;pre class="code C literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="keyword"&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="operator"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name function"&gt;foo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="operator"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="operator"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="name"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="operator"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="operator"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;PyInt_FromLong&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="literal number integer"&gt;1234&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="keyword"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you are in RPython and do a cpyext call to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;foo&lt;/tt&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;RPython-to-C&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;foo&lt;/tt&gt; calls &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyInt_FromLong(1234)&lt;/tt&gt;, which is implemented in RPython:
&lt;strong&gt;C-to-RPython&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the implementation of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyInt_FromLong&lt;/tt&gt; indirectly calls
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyIntType.tp_new&lt;/tt&gt;, which is a C function pointer: &lt;strong&gt;RPython-to-C&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;however, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;tp_new&lt;/tt&gt; is just a wrapper around an RPython function, created
by &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;_make_wrapper&lt;/tt&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;C-to-RPython&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finally, we create our RPython &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_IntObject(1234)&lt;/tt&gt;; at some point
during the &lt;strong&gt;RPython-to-C&lt;/strong&gt; crossing, its &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; equivalent is
created;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;after many layers of wrappers, we are again in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;foo&lt;/tt&gt;: after we do
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;return result&lt;/tt&gt;, during the &lt;strong&gt;C-to-RPython&lt;/strong&gt; step we convert it from
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_IntObject(1234)&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Phew! After we realized this, it was not so surprising that &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; was very
slow :). And this was a simplified example, since we are not passing a
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; to the API call. When we do, we need to convert it back and
forth at every step.  Actually, I am not even sure that what I described was
the exact sequence of steps which used to happen, but you get the general
idea.&lt;br&gt;
The solution is simple: rewrite as much as we can in C instead of RPython,
to avoid unnecessary roundtrips. This was the topic of most of the Cape Town
sprint and resulted in the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;cpyext-avoid-roundtrip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; branch, which was
eventually &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/tree/branch/cpyext_avoid-roundtrip"&gt;merged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Of course, it is not possible to move &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt; to C: there are still
operations which need to be implemented in RPython. For example, think of
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyList_Append&lt;/tt&gt;: the logic to append an item to a list is complex and
involves list strategies, so we cannot replicate it in C.  However, we
discovered that a large subset of the C API can benefit from this.&lt;br&gt;
Moreover, the C API is &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt;. While we invented this new way of writing
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; code, we still need to
convert many of the functions to the new paradigm.  Sometimes the rewrite is
not automatic
or straighforward. &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; is a delicate piece of software, so it happens often
that we make a mistake and end up staring at a segfault in gdb.&lt;br&gt;
However, the most important takeaway is that the performance improvements we got
from this optimization are impressive, as we will detail later.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conversion-costs"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
Conversion costs&lt;/h1&gt;
The other potential big source of slowdown is the conversion of arguments
between &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
As explained earlier, the first time you pass a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; to C, you need to
allocate its &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; counterpart. Suppose you have a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;foo&lt;/tt&gt; function
defined in C, which takes a single int argument:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;pre class="code python literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="keyword"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="operator word"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name builtin"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="name"&gt;foo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
To run this code, you need to create a different &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; for each value
of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;i&lt;/tt&gt;: if implemented naively, it means calling &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;N&lt;/tt&gt; times &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;malloc()&lt;/tt&gt;
and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;free()&lt;/tt&gt;, which kills performance.&lt;br&gt;
CPython has the very same problem, which is solved by using a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_list"&gt;free list&lt;/a&gt; to
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/python/cpython/blob/2.7/Objects/intobject.c#L16"&gt;allocate ints&lt;/a&gt;. So, what we did was to simply &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/commit/d8754ab9ba6371c83eaeb80cdf8cc13a37ee0c89"&gt;steal the code&lt;/a&gt; from CPython
and do the exact same thing. This was also done in the
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;cpyext-avoid-roundtrip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; branch, and the benchmarks show that it worked
perfectly.&lt;br&gt;
Every type which is converted often to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; must have a very fast
allocator. At the moment of writing, PyPy uses free lists only for ints and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/commit/35e2fb9903f2483940d7970bd83ce8c65aa1c1a3"&gt;tuples&lt;/a&gt;: one of the next steps on our TODO list is certainly to use this
technique with more types, like &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;float&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Conversely, we also need to optimize the conversion from &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; to
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt;: this happens when an object is originally allocated in C and
returned to Python. Consider for example the following code:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;pre class="code python literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="keyword namespace"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name namespace"&gt;numpy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="keyword namespace"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name namespace"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="name"&gt;myarray&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="operator"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="operator"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="operator"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="keyword"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="operator word"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="name builtin"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name builtin"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;arr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="name"&gt;myarray&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="name"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="punctuation"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
At every iteration, we get an item out of the array: the return type is a an
instance of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;numpy.float64&lt;/tt&gt; (a numpy scalar), i.e. a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject'*&lt;/tt&gt;: this is
something which is implemented by numpy entirely in C, so completely
opaque to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt;. We don't have any control on how it is allocated,
managed, etc., and we can assume that allocation costs are the same as on
CPython.&lt;br&gt;
As soon as we return these &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; to Python, we need to allocate
their &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; equivalent. If you do it in a small loop like in the example
above, you end up allocating all these &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; inside the nursery, which is
a good thing since allocation is super fast (see the section above about the
PyPy GC).&lt;br&gt;
However, we also need to keep track of the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;W_Root&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; link.
Currently, we do this by putting all of them in a dictionary, but it is very
inefficient, especially because most of these objects die young and thus it
is wasted work to do that for them.  Currently, this is one of the biggest
unresolved problem in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt;, and it is what causes the two microbenchmarks
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;allocate_int&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;allocate_tuple&lt;/tt&gt; to be very slow.&lt;br&gt;
We are well aware of the problem, and we have a plan for how to fix it. The
explanation is too technical for the scope of this blog post as it requires a
deep knowledge of the GC internals to be understood, but the details are
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/extradoc/-/blob/branch/extradoc/planning/cpyext.txt#L27"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="c-api-quirks"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
C API quirks&lt;/h1&gt;
Finally, there is another source of slowdown which is beyond our control. Some
parts of the CPython C API are badly designed and expose some of the
implementation details of CPython.&lt;br&gt;
The major example is reference counting. The &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Py_INCREF&lt;/tt&gt; / &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Py_DECREF&lt;/tt&gt; API
is designed in such a way which forces other implementation to emulate
refcounting even in presence of other GC management schemes, as explained
above.&lt;br&gt;
Another example is borrowed references. There are API functions which &lt;strong&gt;do
not&lt;/strong&gt; incref an object before returning it, e.g. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/2/c-api/list.html#c.PyList_GetItem"&gt;PyList_GetItem()&lt;/a&gt;.  This is
done for performance reasons because we can avoid a whole incref/decref pair,
if the caller needs to handle the returned item only temporarily: the item is
kept alive because it is in the list anyway.&lt;br&gt;
For PyPy, this is a challenge: thanks to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pypy.org/posts/2011/10/more-compact-lists-with-list-strategies-8229304944653956829.html"&gt;list strategies&lt;/a&gt;, lists are often
represented in a compact way. For example, a list containing only integers is
stored as a C array of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;long&lt;/tt&gt;.  How to implement &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyList_GetItem&lt;/tt&gt;? We
cannot simply create a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt; on the fly, because the caller will never
decref it and it will result in a memory leak.&lt;br&gt;
The current solution is very inefficient. The first time we do a
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyList_GetItem&lt;/tt&gt;, we &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/tree/branch/py3.6/pypy/module/cpyext/listobject.py#lines-28"&gt;convert&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;strong&gt;whole&lt;/strong&gt; list to a list of
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;. This is bad in two ways: the first is that we potentially pay a
lot of unneeded conversion cost in case we will never access the other items
of the list. The second is that by doing that we lose all the performance
benefit granted by the original list strategy, making it slower for the
rest of the pure-python code which will manipulate the list later.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyList_GetItem&lt;/tt&gt; is an example of a bad API because it assumes that the list
is implemented as an array of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyObject*&lt;/tt&gt;: after all, in order to return a
borrowed reference, we need a reference to borrow, don't we?&lt;br&gt;
Fortunately, (some) CPython developers are aware of these problems, and there
is an ongoing project to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://pythoncapi.readthedocs.io/"&gt;design a better C API&lt;/a&gt; which aims to fix exactly
this kind of problem.&lt;br&gt;
Nonetheless, in the meantime we still need to implement the current
half-broken APIs. There is no easy solution for that, and it is likely that
we will always need to pay some performance penalty in order to implement them
correctly.&lt;br&gt;
However, what we could potentially do is to provide alternative functions
which do the same job but are more PyPy friendly: for example, we could think
of implementing &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PyList_GetItemNonBorrowed&lt;/tt&gt; or something like that: then, C
extensions could choose to use it (possibly hidden inside some macro and
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;#ifdef&lt;/tt&gt;) if they want to be fast on PyPy.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="current-performance"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
Current performance&lt;/h1&gt;
During the whole blog post we claimed &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; is slow. How
slow it is, exactly?&lt;br&gt;
We decided to concentrate on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/antocuni/cpyext-benchmarks"&gt;microbenchmarks&lt;/a&gt; for now. It should be evident
by now there are simply too many issues which can slow down a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt;
program, and microbenchmarks help us to concentrate on one (or few) at a
time.&lt;br&gt;
The microbenchmarks measure very simple things, like calling functions and
methods with the various calling conventions (no arguments, one arguments,
multiple arguments); passing various types as arguments (to measure conversion
costs); allocating objects from C, and so on.&lt;br&gt;
Here are the results from the old PyPy 5.8 relative and normalized to CPython
2.7, the lower the better:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;


&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-5QV9jBfeXfo/W6UOCRA9YqI/AAAAAAAABX4/H2zgbv_XFQEHD4Lb2lj5Ve4Ob_YMuSXLwCLcBGAs/s1600/pypy58.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="480" src="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-5QV9jBfeXfo/W6UOCRA9YqI/AAAAAAAABX4/H2zgbv_XFQEHD4Lb2lj5Ve4Ob_YMuSXLwCLcBGAs/s640/pypy58.png" width="640"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=3971202189709462152" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=3971202189709462152" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
PyPy was horribly slow everywhere, ranging from 2.5x to 10x slower. It is
particularly interesting to compare &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;simple.noargs&lt;/tt&gt;, which measures the cost
of calling an empty function with no arguments, and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;simple.onearg(i)&lt;/tt&gt;,
which measures the cost calling an empty function passing an integer argument:
the latter is ~2x slower than the former, indicating that the conversion cost
of integers is huge.&lt;br&gt;
PyPy 5.8 was the last release before the famous Cape Town sprint, when we
started to look at cpyext performance seriously. Here are the performance data for
PyPy 6.0, the latest release at the time of writing:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-MRkRoxtCeOE/W6UOL5txl1I/AAAAAAAABX8/i0ZiOyS2MOgiSyxFAyMOkKcB6xqjSihBACLcBGAs/s1600/pypy60.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="480" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-MRkRoxtCeOE/W6UOL5txl1I/AAAAAAAABX8/i0ZiOyS2MOgiSyxFAyMOkKcB6xqjSihBACLcBGAs/s640/pypy60.png" width="640"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The results are amazing! PyPy is now massively faster than before, and for
most benchmarks it is even faster than CPython: yes, you read it correctly:
PyPy is faster than CPython at doing CPython's job, even considering all the
extra work it has to do to emulate the C API.  This happens thanks to the JIT,
which produces speedups high enough to counterbalance the slowdown caused by
cpyext.&lt;br&gt;
There are two microbenchmarks which are still slower though: &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;allocate_int&lt;/tt&gt;
and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;allocate_tuple&lt;/tt&gt;, for the reasons explained in the section about
&lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=3971202189709462152#conversion-costs"&gt;Conversion costs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="next-steps"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;
Next steps&lt;/h1&gt;
Despite the spectacular results we got so far, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; is still slow enough to
kill performance in most real-world code which uses C extensions extensively
(e.g., the omnipresent numpy).&lt;br&gt;
Our current approach is something along these lines:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run a real-world small benchmark which exercises cpyext&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;measure and find the major bottleneck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;write a corresponding microbenchmark&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;optimize it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
On one hand, this is a daunting task because the C API is huge and we need to
tackle functions one by one.  On the other hand, not all the functions are
equally important, and is is enough to optimize a relatively small subset to
improve many different use cases.&lt;br&gt;
Where a year ago we announced we have a working answer to run c-extension in
PyPy, we now have a clear picture of what are the performance bottlenecks, and
we have developed some technical solutions to fix them. It is "only" a matter
of tackling them, one by one.  It is worth noting that most of the work was
done during two sprints, for a total 2-3 person-months of work.&lt;br&gt;
We think this work is important for the Python ecosystem. PyPy has established
a baseline for performance in pure python code, providing an answer for the
"Python is slow" detractors. The techniques used to make &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; performant
will let PyPy become an alternative for people who mix C extensions with
Python, which, it turns out, is just about everyone, in particular those using
the various scientific libraries. Today, many developers are forced to seek
performance by converting code from Python to a lower language. We feel there
is no reason to do this, but in order to prove it we must be able to run both
their python and their C extensions performantly, then we can begin to educate
them how to write JIT-friendly code in the first place.&lt;br&gt;
We envision a future in which you can run arbitrary Python programs on PyPy,
with the JIT speeding up the pure Python parts and the C parts running as fast
as today: the best of both worlds!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cpyext</category><category>profiling</category><category>speed</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2018/09/inside-cpyext-why-emulating-cpython-c-8083064623681286567.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2018 16:32:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>(Cape of) Good Hope for PyPy</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2017/10/cape-of-good-hope-for-pypy-hello-from-3656631725712879033.html</link><dc:creator>Antonio Cuni</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Hello from the other side of the world (for most of you)!&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
With the excuse of coming to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://za.pycon.org/"&gt;PyCon ZA&lt;/a&gt; during the last two weeks Armin,
Ronan, Antonio and sometimes Maciek had a very nice and productive sprint in
Cape Town, as pictures show :). We would like to say a big thank you to
Kiwi.com, which sponsored part of the travel costs via its awesome &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kiwi.com/sourcelift/"&gt;Sourcelift&lt;/a&gt;
program to help Open Source projects.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: right; margin-left: 1em; text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-9YVNucPN1wE/WeaWmTUFB-I/AAAAAAAABMQ/HeVMqS-ya2IYJuk0iZZODlULqpKaf5XcgCLcBGAs/s1600/DSC_2418.JPG" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="225" src="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-9YVNucPN1wE/WeaWmTUFB-I/AAAAAAAABMQ/HeVMqS-ya2IYJuk0iZZODlULqpKaf5XcgCLcBGAs/s400/DSC_2418.JPG" width="400"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Armin, Anto and Ronan at Cape Point&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Armin, Ronan and Anto spent most of the time hacking at cpyext, our CPython
C-API compatibility layer: during the last years, the focus was to make it
working and compatible with CPython, in order to run existing libraries such
as numpy and pandas. However, we never paid too much attention to performance,
so the net result is that with the latest released version of PyPy, C
extensions generally work but their speed ranges from "slow" to "horribly
slow".&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
For example, these very simple &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/antocuni/cpyext-benchmarks"&gt;microbenchmarks&lt;/a&gt; measure the speed of
calling (empty) C functions, i.e. the time you spend to "cross the border"
between RPython and C.  &lt;i&gt;(Note: this includes the time spent doing the loop in regular Python code.)&lt;/i&gt; These are the results on CPython, on PyPy 5.8, and on
our newest in-progress version:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;$ python bench.py     # CPython
noargs      : 0.41 secs
onearg(None): 0.44 secs
onearg(i)   : 0.44 secs
varargs     : 0.58 secs
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;$ pypy-5.8 bench.py   # PyPy 5.8
noargs      : 1.01 secs
onearg(None): 1.31 secs
onearg(i)   : 2.57 secs
varargs     : 2.79 secs
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;$ pypy bench.py       # cpyext-refactor-methodobject branch
noargs      : 0.17 secs
onearg(None): 0.21 secs
onearg(i)   : 0.22 secs
varargs     : 0.47 secs
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
So yes: before the sprint, we were ~2-6x slower than CPython. Now, we are
&lt;strong&gt;faster&lt;/strong&gt; than it!
To reach this result, we did various improvements, such as:
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teach the JIT how to look (a bit) inside the cpyext module;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;write specialized code for calling &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;METH_NOARGS&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;METH_O&lt;/tt&gt; and
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;METH_VARARGS&lt;/tt&gt; functions; previously, we always used a very general and
slow logic;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;implement freelists to allocate the cpyext versions of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;int&lt;/tt&gt; and
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;tuple&lt;/tt&gt; objects, as CPython does;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/pypy/-/merge_requests/573"&gt;cpyext-avoid-roundtrip&lt;/a&gt; branch: crossing the RPython/C border is
slowish, but the real problem was (and still is for many cases) we often
cross it many times for no good reason. So, depending on the actual API
call, you might end up in the C land, which calls back into the RPython
land, which goes to C, etc. etc. (ad libitum).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The branch tries to fix such nonsense: so far, we fixed only some cases, which
are enough to speed up the benchmarks shown above.  But most importantly, we
now have a clear path and an actual plan to improve cpyext more and
more. Ideally, we would like to reach a point in which cpyext-intensive
programs run at worst at the same speed of CPython.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The other big topic of the sprint was Armin and Maciej doing a lot of work on the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/pypy/pypy/commits/branch/unicode-utf8"&gt;unicode-utf8&lt;/a&gt; branch: the goal of the branch is to always use UTF-8 as the
internal representation of unicode strings. The advantages are various:
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;decoding a UTF-8 stream is super fast, as you just need to check that the
stream is valid;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;encoding to UTF-8 is almost a no-op;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UTF-8 is always more compact representation than the currently
used UCS-4. It's also almost always more compact than CPython 3.5 latin1/UCS2/UCS4 combo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;smaller representation means everything becomes quite a bit faster due to lower cache pressure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Before you ask: yes, this branch contains special logic to ensure that random
access of single unicode chars is still O(1), as it is on both CPython and the
current PyPy.&lt;br&gt;
We also plan to improve the speed of decoding even more by using modern processor features, like SSE and AVX. Preliminary results show that decoding can be done 100x faster than the current setup.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
In summary, this was a long and profitable sprint, in which we achieved lots
of interesting results. However, what we liked even more was the privilege of
doing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/pypy/pypy/commits/a4307fb5912e"&gt;commits&lt;/a&gt; from awesome places such as the top of Table Mountain:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;
&lt;div dir="ltr" lang="en"&gt;
Our sprint venue today &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/pypy?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#pypy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/o38IfTYmAV"&gt;pic.twitter.com/o38IfTYmAV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
— Ronan Lamy (@ronanlamy) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ronanlamy/status/915575026107240449?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;4 ottobre 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;br&gt;
&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/extradoc/-/blob/branch/extradoc/sprintinfo/cape-town-2017/2017-10-04-155524.jpg" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="360" src="https://bytebucket.org/pypy/extradoc/raw/extradoc/sprintinfo/cape-town-2017/2017-10-04-155524.jpg" width="640"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;The panorama we looked at instead of staring at cpyext code&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>cpyext</category><category>profiling</category><category>speed</category><category>sprint</category><category>unicode</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2017/10/cape-of-good-hope-for-pypy-hello-from-3656631725712879033.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 13:31:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Using CPython extension modules with PyPy natively, or: PyPy can load .pyd files with CPyExt!</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2010/04/using-cpython-extension-modules-with-5864754772659599217.html</link><dc:creator>Alexander Schremmer</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;PyPy is now able to load
and run CPython extension modules (i.e. .pyd and .so files) natively by using the new CPyExt
subsystem.
Unlike the solution presented in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pypy.org/posts/2009/11/using-cpython-extension-modules-with-4951018896657992031.html"&gt;another blog post&lt;/a&gt; (where extension modules like
numpy etc. were run on CPython and proxied through TCP), this solution does not require
a running CPython anymore. We do not achieve full binary compatiblity
yet (like Ironclad), but recompiling the extension is generally enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only prerequisite is that the necessary functions of the C API of CPython are already
implemented in PyPy. If you are a user or an author of a module and miss certain functions
in PyPy, we invite you to implement them. Up until now, a lot of people (including a lot of
new committers) have stepped up and implemented a few functions to get their favorite module
running. See the end of this post for a list of names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding speed, we tried the following: even though there is a bit of overhead when running
these modules, we could run the regular expression engine of CPython (&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;_sre.so&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;) and execute
the spambayes benchmark of the Unladen Swallow benchmark suite (cf. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://speed.pypy.org/"&gt;speed.pypy.org&lt;/a&gt;) and
experience a speedup:
It became &lt;em&gt;two times faster&lt;/em&gt; on pypy-c than with the built-in regular
expression engine of PyPy. From &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amdahl%27s_law"&gt;Amdahl's Law&lt;/a&gt; it follows that the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;_sre.so&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; must run several
times faster than the built-in engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently pursued modules include PIL and others. Distutils support is nearly ready.
If you would like to participate or want information on how to use this new feature, come and join
our IRC channel &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;#pypy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="irc://irc.freenode.net/"&gt;freenode&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amaury Forgeot d'Arc and Alexander Schremmer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further CPyExt Contributors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Alex Gaynor
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Benjamin Peterson
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Jean-Paul Calderone
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Maciej Fijalkowski
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Jan de Mooij
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lucian Branescu Mihaila
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Andreas Stührk
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Zooko Wilcox-O Hearn&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>cpyext</category><category>CPython</category><category>extension modules</category><category>speed</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2010/04/using-cpython-extension-modules-with-5864754772659599217.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2010 22:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>