<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PyPy (Posts by Armin Rigo)</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.pypy.org/authors/armin-rigo.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2026 &lt;a href="mailto:pypy-dev@pypy.org"&gt;The PyPy Team&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 00:22:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Mac meets Arm64</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/12/mac-meets-arm64-940822335619099039.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;b&gt;Looking for sponsorship&lt;/b&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple now ships Macs which are running on an arm64 variant machine with the
latest version of MacOS, Big Sur M1.  We are getting requests for PyPy to
support this new architecture.  Here is our position on this topic (or at least
mine, Armin Rigo's), and how you can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porting PyPy is harder than just re-running the compiler, because PyPy contains
a few big architecture-dependent "details", like the JIT compiler and the
foreign function interfaces (CFFI and ctypes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixing the JIT compiler should not be too much work: we already support arm64,
just the Linux one.  But Apple made various details different (like the calling
conventions).  A few other parts need to be fixed too, notably CFFI and ctypes,
again because of the calling conventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixing that would be a reasonable amount of work.  I would do it myself for a
small amount of money.  However, the story doesn't finish here.  Obviously, the
&lt;b&gt;start&lt;/b&gt; of the story would be to get ssh access to a Big Sur M1 machine.  (If at
this point you're thinking "sure, I can give you ssh access for three months",
then please read on.)  The &lt;b&gt;next&lt;/b&gt; part of the story is that we need a machine
available long term.  It can be either a machine provided and maintained by a
third party, or alternatively a pot of money big enough to support the
acquision of a machine and ongoing work of one of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we go with the provided-machine solution:  What we need isn't a lot of
resources.  Our CI requires maybe 10 GB of disk space, and a few hours of CPU
per run.  It should fit into 8 GB of RAM.  We normally do a run every night but
we can certainly lower the frequency a bit if that would help.  However, we'd
ideally like some kind of assurance that you are invested into maintaining the
machine for the next 3-5 years (I guess, see below).  We had far too many
machines that disappeared after a few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we go with the money-supported solution: it's likely that after 3-5 years
the whole Mac base will have switched to arm64, we'll drop x86-64 support for
Mac, and we'll be back to the situation of the past where there was only one
kind of Mac machine to care about.  In the meantime, we are looking at 3-5
years of lightweight extra maintenance.  We have someone that has said he would
do it, but not for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If either of these two solutions occurs, we'll still have, I quote, "probably
some changes in distutils-type stuff to make python happy", and then some
packaging/deployment changes to support the  "universal2" architecture, i.e.
including both versions inside a single executable (which will &lt;b&gt;not&lt;/b&gt; be just an
extra switch to clang, because the two versions need a different JIT backend
and so must be translated separately).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now all the factors are on the table.  We won't do the minimal "just the
JIT compiler fixes" if we don't have a plan that goes farther.  Either we get
sufficient money, and maybe support, and then we can do it quickly; or PyPy
will just remain not natively available on M1 hardware for the next 3-5 years.
We are looking forward to supporting M1, and view resources contributed by
the community as a vote of confidence in assuring the future of PyPy on this
hardware.  Contact us: &lt;a href="mailto:pypy-dev@python.org"&gt;pypy-dev@python.org&lt;/a&gt;, or our private mailing
list &lt;a href="mailto:pypy-z@python.org"&gt;pypy-z@python.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armin Rigo&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/12/mac-meets-arm64-940822335619099039.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 09:53:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PyPy is on Open Collective</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/08/pypy-is-on-open-collective-5673322428814364737.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PyPy is now a &lt;a href="https://opencollective.com/pypy"&gt;member of Open Collective&lt;/a&gt;, a fiscal host.  We have been thinking about switching to this organization for a couple of years; we like it for various reasons, like the budget transparency and the lightweight touch.  We can now officially announce our membership!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this, we are now again free to use PyPy for all financial issues, like receiving funds professionally, paying parts of sprint budgets as we like, and so on.  We will shortly be reintroducing buttons that link to Open Collective from the PyPy web site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the old donation buttons were removed last year, we believe that there are still a few people that send regularly money to the SFC, the not-for-profit charity we were affiliated with.  If you do, please stop doing it now (and, if you like to do so, please set up an equivalent donation to &lt;a href="https://opencollective.com/pypy"&gt;PyPy on Open Collective&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And by the way, sorry for all of you who were getting mixed feelings from the previous blog post (co-written with the SFC).  &lt;b&gt;PyPy is committed to continue being Open Source just like before.&lt;/b&gt;  This was never in question.  What these two blog posts mean is only that we switched to a different organization for our internal finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We're looking forward to how this new relationship will go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armin Rigo, for the PyPy team&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/08/pypy-is-on-open-collective-5673322428814364737.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 11:53:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Leysin Winter sprint 2020: Feb 29 - March 8th</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/01/leysin-winter-sprint-2020-feb-28-march-6349761524797409012.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;a href="https://q-cf.bstatic.com/images/hotel/max1280x900/321/32136520.jpg" style="clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="240" src="https://q-cf.bstatic.com/images/hotel/max1280x900/321/32136520.jpg" width="320"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The next PyPy sprint will be in Leysin, Switzerland, for the fourteenth
time.  This is a fully public sprint: newcomers and topics other than
those proposed below are welcome.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
Goals and topics of the sprint&lt;/h3&gt;
The list of topics is open.  For reference, we would like to work at least partially on the following topics:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/pyhandle/hpy"&gt;HPy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python 3.7 support (&lt;a href="https://buildbot.pypy.org/summary?branch=py3.7"&gt;buildbot status&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
As usual, the main side goal is to have fun in winter sports :-)
We can take a day off (for ski or anything else).&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
Times and accomodation&lt;/h3&gt;
The sprint will occur for one week starting on Saturday, the 29th of February, to Sunday, the 8th of March 2020 &lt;b&gt;(dates were pushed back one day!)&lt;/b&gt;  It will occur in &lt;a href="https://www.booking.com/hotel/ch/les-airelles.html"&gt;Les Airelles&lt;/a&gt;, a different bed-and-breakfast place from the traditional one in &lt;span class="il"&gt;Leysin&lt;/span&gt;.  It is a nice old house at the top of the village.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strike&gt;We have a 4- or 5-people room as well as up to three double-rooms.  Please register early!  These rooms are not booked for the sprint in advance, and might be already taken if you end up announcing yourself late.&lt;/strike&gt;  We have a big room for up to 7 people with nice view, which might be split in two or three sub-rooms; plus possibly separately-booked double rooms if needed. (But it is of course always possible to book at a different place in Leysin.)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
For more information, see our &lt;a href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/extradoc/-/blob/branch/default/extradoc/sprintinfo/leysin-winter-2020/"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; or write to me directly at armin.rigo@gmail.com.</description><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/01/leysin-winter-sprint-2020-feb-28-march-6349761524797409012.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 10:36:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A second life for the Sandbox</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2019/08/a-second-life-for-sandbox-6848726729476245390.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all,&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href="https://anvil.works/" target="_blank"&gt;Anvil&lt;/a&gt; is a UK-based company sponsoring one month of work to revive PyPy's
"sandbox" mode and upgrade it to PyPy3.  Thanks to them, sandboxing will be
given a second life!&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The &lt;a href="https://doc.pypy.org/en/latest/sandbox.html"&gt;sandboxed PyPy&lt;/a&gt; is a special version of PyPy that runs
fully isolated.  It gives a safe way to execute arbitrary Python
programs (&lt;i&gt;whole&lt;/i&gt; programs, not small bits of code inside your larger Python
program).  Such scripts can be fully untrusted, and they can try to do
anything—there are no syntax-based restrictions, for example—but whatever
they do, any communication with the external world is not actually done but
delegated to the parent process.  This is similar but much more flexible than
Linux's Seccomp approach, and it is more lightweight than setting up a full
virtual machine.  It also works without operating system support.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
However, during the course of the years the sandbox mode of PyPy has been
mostly unmaintained and unsupported by the core developers, mostly because of
a lack of interest by users and because it took too much effort to maintain
it.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Now we have found that we have an actual user, &lt;a href="https://anvil.works/" target="_blank"&gt;Anvil&lt;/a&gt;.  As far as I can tell
they are still using a very old version of PyPy, the last one that supported
sandboxing. This is where this contract comes from: the goal is to modernize sandboxing and port it to PyPy3.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Part of my motivation for accepting this work is that I may have found a way to
tweak the protocol on the pipe between the sandboxed PyPy and the parent
controller process.  This should make the sandboxed PyPy more resilient against
future developments and easier to maintain; at most, in the future some tweaks will be needed in the
controller process but hopefully not deep inside the guts of the sandboxed
PyPy.  Among the advantages, such a more robust solution should mean that we
can actually get a working sandboxed PyPy—or sandboxed PyPy3 or sandboxed
version of &lt;a href="https://rpython.readthedocs.io/en/latest/examples.html"&gt;any other interpreter written in RPython&lt;/a&gt;—with just an extra
argument when calling &lt;span&gt;rpython&lt;/span&gt; to translate this interpreter.  If everything
works as planned, sandboxing may be given a second life.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Armin Rigo&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2019/08/a-second-life-for-sandbox-6848726729476245390.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2019 18:31:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Leysin Winter Sprint 2018: review</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2018/03/leysin-winter-sprint-2018-review-3988364248531980164.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Like every year, the PyPy developers and a couple of newcomers
      gathered in Leysin, Switzerland, to share their thoughts and
      contribute to the development of PyPy.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As always, we had interesting discussions about how we could
      improve PyPy, to make it the first choice for even more
      developers. We also made some progress with current issues, like
      compatibility with Python 3.6 and improving the performance of
      CPython extension modules, where we fixed a lot of bugs and gained
      new insights about where and how we could tweak PyPy.&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; We were very happy about the number of new people who joined us
      for the first time, and hope they enjoyed it as much as everyone
      else. &lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Topics&lt;/h3&gt;
    We worked on the following topics (and more!):&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Introductions for newcomers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Python 3.5 and 3.6 improvements&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;CPyExt performance improvements and GC implementation&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;JIT: guard-compatible implementation&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pygame performance improvements&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unicode/UTF8 implementation&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;CFFI tutorial/overview rewrite
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;py3 test runners refactoring&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;RevDB improvements&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    The weather was really fine for most of the week, with only
    occasional snow and fog. We started our days with a short (and
    sometimes not so short) planning session and enjoyed our dinners in
    the great restaurants in the area. Some of us even started earlier
    and continued till late night. It was a relaxed, but also very
    productive atmosphere. On our break day on Wednesday, we enjoyed the
    great conditions and went skiing and hiking.
    &lt;h3&gt;Attendees&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Arianna&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jean-Daniel&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stefan Beyer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Floris Bruynooghe&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Antonio Cuni&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;René Dudfield&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Manuel Jacob&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ronan Lamy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Remi Meier&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Matti Picus&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Armin Rigo&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Alexander Schremmer&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    Leysin is easily reachable by Geneva Airport, so feel free to join
    us next time!&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    &lt;br&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;br&gt;
      Stefan&lt;br&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2018/03/leysin-winter-sprint-2018-review-3988364248531980164.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 07:54:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Leysin Winter sprint: 17-24 March 2018</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2018/01/leysin-winter-sprint-17-24-march-2018-7141092581585849418.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;table border="0"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next PyPy sprint will be in Leysin, Switzerland, for the thirteenth
time.  This is a fully public sprint: newcomers and topics other than
those proposed below are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: this sprint is independent from the suggested April-May sprint in
Poland.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Goals and topics of the sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list of topics is open, but here is our current list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HQ8S2DcTato/WIc2XXEQP9I/AAAAAAAAAQw/7BNVgaMg-jcaMzVaAc2JD5sMgu-Xn5DeACLcB/s1600/chalet1_004.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="240" src="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HQ8S2DcTato/WIc2XXEQP9I/AAAAAAAAAQw/7BNVgaMg-jcaMzVaAc2JD5sMgu-Xn5DeACLcB/s320/chalet1_004.jpg" width="320"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; cffi tutorial/overview rewrite
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; py3 test runners are too complicated
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; make win32 builds green
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; make packaging more like cpython/portable builds
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; get CI builders for PyPy into mainstream projects (Numpy, Scipy, lxml, uwsgi)
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; get more of scientific stack working (tensorflow?)
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; cpyext performance improvements
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; General 3.5 and 3.6 improvements
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; JIT topics: guard-compatible, and the subsequent research project to save and reuse traces across processes
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; finish unicode-utf8
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; update www.pypy.org, speed.pypy.org (web devs needed)
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, the main side goal is to have fun in winter sports :-)
We can take a day off (for ski or anything else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Exact times&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work days: starting March 18th (~noon), ending March 24th (~noon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please see &lt;a href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/extradoc/-/blob/branch/default/extradoc/sprintinfo/leysin-winter-2018/announcement.txt"&gt;announcement.txt&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2018/01/leysin-winter-sprint-17-24-march-2018-7141092581585849418.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 10:33:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Leysin Winter Sprint: 25/26th Feb. - 4th March 2017</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2017/01/leysin-winter-sprint-2526th-feb-4th-3831779797804484935.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The next PyPy sprint will be in Leysin, Switzerland, for the twelveth time.
This is a fully public sprint: newcomers and topics other than those
proposed below are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="goals-and-topics-of-the-sprint"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Goals and topics of the sprint&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list of topics is very open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The main topic is Python 3.5 support in PyPy, as most py3.5
contributors should be present.  It is also a good topic if you have
no or limited experience with PyPy contribution: we can easily find
something semi-independent that is not done in py3.5 so far, and
do pair-programming with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any other topic is fine too: JIT compiler optimizations, CFFI,
the RevDB reverse debugger, improving to speed of your program on
PyPy, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And as usual, the main side goal is to have fun in winter sports :-)
We can take a day off (for ski or anything else).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="exact-times"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exact times&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work days: starting 26th Feb (~noon), ending March 4th (~noon).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have pre-booked the week from Saturday Feb 25th to Saturday March 4th.
If it is possible for you to arrive Sunday before mid-afternoon, then
you should get a booking from Sunday only.  The break day should be
around Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is fine to stay a few more days on either side, or conversely to book
for a part of that time only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="location-accomodation"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Location &amp;amp; Accomodation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leysin, Switzerland, "same place as before".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HQ8S2DcTato/WIc2XXEQP9I/AAAAAAAAAQw/7BNVgaMg-jcaMzVaAc2JD5sMgu-Xn5DeACLcB/s1600/chalet1_004.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="240" src="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HQ8S2DcTato/WIc2XXEQP9I/AAAAAAAAAQw/7BNVgaMg-jcaMzVaAc2JD5sMgu-Xn5DeACLcB/s320/chalet1_004.jpg" width="320"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me refresh your
memory: both the sprint venue and the lodging will be in a
pair of chalets built specifically for bed &amp;amp; breakfast:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.ermina.ch/"&gt;https://www.ermina.ch/&lt;/a&gt;.  The place has a good ADSL Internet connection
with wireless installed.  You can also arrange your own lodging
elsewhere (as long as you are in Leysin, you cannot be more than a 15
minutes walk away from the sprint venue).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please &lt;em&gt;confirm&lt;/em&gt; that you are coming so that we can adjust the
reservations as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The options of rooms are a bit more limited than on previous years
because the place for bed-and-breakfast is shrinking; but we should
still have enough room for us.  The price is around 60 CHF, breakfast
included, in shared rooms (3 or 4 people).  If there are people that
would prefer a double or single room, please contact me and we'll see
what choices you have.  There are also a choice of hotels in Leysin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please register by Mercurial:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/pypy/extradoc/"&gt;https://bitbucket.org/pypy/extradoc/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/extradoc/-/blob/branch/default/extradoc/sprintinfo/leysin-winter-2017/"&gt;https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/extradoc/-/blob/branch/default/extradoc/sprintinfo/leysin-winter-2017/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or on the pypy-dev mailing list if you do not yet have check-in rights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://mail.python.org/mailman/listinfo/pypy-dev"&gt;https://mail.python.org/mailman/listinfo/pypy-dev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need a Swiss-to-(insert country here) power adapter.  There will be
some Swiss-to-EU adapters around, and at least one EU-format power strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2017/01/leysin-winter-sprint-2526th-feb-4th-3831779797804484935.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 11:01:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>RevDB released, v5.4.1</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2016/09/revdb-released-v541-6719768292347391304.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first beta version of &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/pypy/revdb/"&gt;RevDB&lt;/a&gt; is out!  &lt;a href="https://www.pypy.org/posts/2016/07/reverse-debugging-for-python-8854823774141612670.html"&gt;Remember&lt;/a&gt; that RevDB is a reverse debugger for Python.  The idea is that it is a debugger that can run forward and backward in time, letting you more easily understand your subtle bug in your big Python program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
RevDB should work on almost any Python program.  Even if you are normally only using CPython, trying to reproduce the bug with RevDB is similar to trying to run the program on a regular PyPy---usually it just works, &lt;a href="https://pypy.org/compat.html"&gt;even if not quite always&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
News from the alpha version in the &lt;a href="https://www.pypy.org/posts/2016/07/reverse-debugging-for-python-8854823774141612670.html"&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; include notably support for:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Threads.
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;CPyExt, the compatibility layer of PyPy that can run CPython C extension modules.
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
as well as many other improvements.

&lt;p&gt;
You need to build it yourself for now.  It is tested on 64-bit Linux.  32-bit Linux, OS/X, and other POSIX platforms should all either work out of the box or be just a few fixes away (contributions welcome).  Win32 support is a lot more involved but not impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
See &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/pypy/revdb/"&gt;https://bitbucket.org/pypy/revdb/&lt;/a&gt; for more information!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armin&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>releaserevdb</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2016/09/revdb-released-v541-6719768292347391304.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 09:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PyPy gets funding from Mozilla for Python 3.5 support</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2016/08/pypy-gets-funding-from-mozilla-for-5569307998787871200.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;"Python 2.x versus Python 3.x": this is by now an old question.  In the eyes of some people Python 2 is here to stay, and in the eyes of others Python has long been 3 only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PyPy's own position is that PyPy will support Python 2.7 forever---the RPython language in which PyPy is written is a subset of  2.7, and we have no plan to upgrade that.  But at the same time, we want to support 3.x.  This is particularly true now: a relatively recent development is that Python 3.5 seems to attract more and more people.  The "switch" to Python 3.x might be starting to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correspondingly, PyPy has been searching for a while for a way to support a larger-scale development effort.  The goal is to support not just any old version of Python 3.x, but Python 3.5, as this seems to be the version that people are switching to.  PyPy is close to supporting all of Python 3.3 now; but the list of what is new in Python &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/whatsnew/3.4.html"&gt;3.4&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/whatsnew/3.5.html"&gt;3.5&lt;/a&gt; is far, far longer than anyone imagines.  The long-term goal is also to get a version of "PyPy3" that is as good as "PyPy2" is, including its performance and its cpyext layer (CPython C API interoperability), for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the end result: &lt;a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/blog/2016/08/04/mozilla-awards-585000-to-nine-open-source-projects-in-q2-2016/"&gt;Mozilla recently decided to award $200,000&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://baroquesoftware.com/"&gt;Baroque Software&lt;/a&gt; to work on PyPy as part of its Mozilla Open Source Support (MOSS) initiative.  This money will be used to implement the Python 3.5 features in PyPy. Within the next year, we plan to use the money to pay four core PyPy developers half-time to work on the missing features and on some of the big performance and cpyext issues. This should speed up the progress of catching up with Python 3.x significantly. We are extremely thankful to Mozilla for supporting us in this way, and will keep you updated on the progress via this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>sponsors</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2016/08/pypy-gets-funding-from-mozilla-for-5569307998787871200.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 16:38:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Reverse debugging for Python</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2016/07/reverse-debugging-for-python-8854823774141612670.html</link><dc:creator>Armin Rigo</dc:creator><description>&lt;div class="section" id="revpdb"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;RevPDB&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A "reverse debugger" is a debugger where you can go forward and
backward in time.  It is an uncommon feature, at least in the open
source world, but I have no idea why.  I have used &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://undo.io/"&gt;undodb-gdb&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rr-project.org/"&gt;rr&lt;/a&gt;, which are reverse debuggers for C code, and I can only say that
they saved me many, many days of poking around blindly in gdb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PyPy team is pleased to give you "RevPDB", a reverse-debugger
similar to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;rr&lt;/tt&gt; but for Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example is worth a thousand words.  Let's say your big Python
program has a bug that shows up inconsistently.  You have nailed it
down to something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;start &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;x.py&lt;/tt&gt;, which does stuff (maybe involving processing files,
answering some web requests that you simulate from another terminal,
etc.);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sometimes, after a few minutes, your program's state becomes
inconsistent and you get a failing assert or another exception.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the case where RevPDB is useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RevPDB is available only on 64-bit Linux and OS/X right now, but should
not be too hard to port to other OSes.  It is very much &lt;em&gt;alpha-level!&lt;/em&gt;
(It is a debugger full of bugs.  Sorry about that.)  I believe it is
still useful---it helped me in one &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/pypy/pypy/commits/bd220c268bc9"&gt;real use case&lt;/a&gt; already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-to-get-revpdb"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How to get RevPDB&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following demo was done with an alpha version for 64-bit Linux,
compiled for Arch Linux.  I won't provide the binary; it should be
easy enough to retranslate (much faster than a regular PyPy because it
contains neither a JIT nor a custom GC).  Grab the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://pypy.org/download.html#building-from-source"&gt;PyPy sources&lt;/a&gt; from
Mercurial, and then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
hg update reverse-debugger
# or "hg update ff376ccacb36" for exactly this demo
cd pypy/goal
../../rpython/bin/rpython -O2 --revdb targetpypystandalone.py  \
                  --withoutmod-cpyext --withoutmod-micronumpy
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and possibly rename the final &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pypy-c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pypy-revdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; to avoid
confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other platforms than 64-bit Linux and OS/X need some fixes before they work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="demo"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Demo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this demo, we're going to use this &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;x.py&lt;/tt&gt; as the "big program":&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
import os

class Foo(object):
    value = 5

lst1 = [Foo() for i in range(100)]
lst1[50].value += 1
for x in lst1:
    x.value += 1

for x in lst1:
    if x.value != 6:
        print 'oops!'
        os._exit(1)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it is clear what occurs in this small example: the check
fails on item 50.  For this demo, the check has been written with
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;os._exit(1)&lt;/tt&gt;, because this exits immediately the program.  If it
was written with an &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;assert&lt;/tt&gt;, then its failure would execute things
in the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;traceback&lt;/tt&gt; module afterwards, to print the traceback; it
would be a minor mess just to find the exact point of the failing
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;assert&lt;/tt&gt;.  (This and other issues are supposed to be fixed in the
future, but for now it is alpha-level.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, with a regular &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;assert&lt;/tt&gt; and a regular post-mortem &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;pdb&lt;/tt&gt;,
we could observe that &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;x.value&lt;/tt&gt; is indeed 7 instead of 6 when the
assert fails.  Imagine that the program is much bigger: how would we
find the exact chain of events that caused this value 7 to show up on
this particular &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Foo&lt;/tt&gt; object?  This is what RevPDB is for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strike&gt;First, we need for now to disable Address Space Layout Randomization
(ASLR), otherwise replaying will not work.  This is done once with the
following command line, which changes the state until the next
reboot:&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
echo 0 | sudo tee /proc/sys/kernel/randomize_va_space
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; the above is no longer necessary from revision ff376ccacb36.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;x.py&lt;/tt&gt; with RevPDB's version of PyPy instead of the regular
interpreter (CPython or PyPy):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
PYPYRDB=log.rdb ./pypy-revdb x.py
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pypy-revdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; executable is like a slow PyPy executable, running
(for now) without a JIT.  This produces a file &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;log.rdb&lt;/tt&gt; which
contains a complete log of this execution.  (If the bug we are
tracking occurs rarely, we need to re-run it several times until we
get the failure.  But once we got the failure, then we're done with
this step.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
rpython/translator/revdb/revdb.py log.rdb
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We get a pdb-style debugger.  This &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;revdb.py&lt;/tt&gt; is a normal Python
program, which you run with an unmodified Python; internally, it looks
inside the log for the path to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pypy-revdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; and run it as needed (as
one forking subprocess, in a special mode).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, we are at the start of the program---not at the end, like
we'd get in a regular debugger:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
File "&amp;lt;builtin&amp;gt;/app_main.py", line 787 in setup_bootstrap_path:
(1)$
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list of commands is available with &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;help&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to the end with &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;continue&lt;/tt&gt; (or &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;c&lt;/tt&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
(1)$ continue
File "/tmp/x.py", line 14 in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;:
...
  lst1 = [Foo() for i in range(100)]
  lst1[50].value += 1
  for x in lst1:
      x.value += 1

  for x in lst1:
      if x.value != 6:
          print 'oops!'
&amp;gt;         os._exit(1)
(19727)$
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are now at the beginning of the last executed line.  The number
19727 is the "time", measured in number of lines executed.  We can go
backward with the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;bstep&lt;/tt&gt; command (backward step, or &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;bs&lt;/tt&gt;), line
by line, and forward again with the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;step&lt;/tt&gt; command.  There are also
commands &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;bnext&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;bcontinue&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;bfinish&lt;/tt&gt; and their forward
equivalents.  There is also "&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;go TIME&lt;/tt&gt;" to jump directly to the specified
time.  (Right now the debugger only stops at "line start"
events, not at function entry or exit, which makes some cases a bit
surprising: for example, a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;step&lt;/tt&gt; from the return statement of
function &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;foo()&lt;/tt&gt; will jump directly to the caller's caller, if the
caller's current line was &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;return foo() + 2&lt;/tt&gt;, because no "line
start" event occurs in the caller after &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;foo()&lt;/tt&gt; returns to it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can print Python expressions and statements using the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;p&lt;/tt&gt;
command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
(19727)$ p x
$0 = &amp;lt;__main__.Foo object at 0xfffffffffffeab3e&amp;gt;
(19727)$ p x.value
$1 = 7
(19727)$ p x.value + 1
8
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$NUM =&lt;/tt&gt;" prefix is only shown when we print an object that
really exists in the debugged program; that's why the last line does
not contain it.  Once a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$NUM&lt;/tt&gt; has been printed, then we can use
it in further expressions---even at a different point time.  It
becomes an anchor that always refers to the same object:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
(19727)$ bstep

File "/tmp/x.py", line 13 in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;:
...

  lst1 = [Foo() for i in range(100)]
  lst1[50].value += 1
  for x in lst1:
      x.value += 1

  for x in lst1:
      if x.value != 6:
&amp;gt;         print 'oops!'
          os._exit(1)
(19726)$ p $0.value
$1 = 7
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, we want to know when this value 7 was put in this
attribute.  This is the job of a watchpoint:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
(19726)$ watch $0.value
Watchpoint 1 added
updating watchpoint value: $0.value =&amp;gt; 7
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This watchpoint means that &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$0.value&lt;/tt&gt; will be evaluated at each line.
When the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;repr()&lt;/tt&gt; of this expression changes, the watchpoint activates
and execution stops:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
(19726)$ bcontinue
[searching 19629..19726]
[searching 19338..19629]

updating watchpoint value: $0.value =&amp;gt; 6
Reverse-hit watchpoint 1: $0.value
File "/tmp/x.py", line 9 in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;:
  import os

  class Foo(object):
      value = 5

  lst1 = [Foo() for i in range(100)]
  lst1[50].value += 1
  for x in lst1:
&amp;gt;     x.value += 1

  for x in lst1:
      if x.value != 6:
          print 'oops!'
          os._exit(1)
(19524)$
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that using the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$NUM&lt;/tt&gt; syntax is essential in watchpoints.  You
can't say "&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;watch x.value&lt;/tt&gt;", because the variable &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;x&lt;/tt&gt; will go out
of scope very soon when we move forward or backward in time.  In fact
the watchpoint expression is always evaluated inside an environment
that contains the builtins but not the current locals and globals.
But it also contains all the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$NUM&lt;/tt&gt;, which can be used to refer to
known objects.  It is thus common to watch &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$0.attribute&lt;/tt&gt; if &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$0&lt;/tt&gt;
is an object, or to watch &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;len($1)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; if &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$1&lt;/tt&gt; is some list.  The
watch expression can also be a simple boolean: for example, "&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;watch
$2 in $3&lt;/tt&gt;" where &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$3&lt;/tt&gt; is some dict and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$2&lt;/tt&gt; is some object that
you find now in the dict; you would use this to find out the time when
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$2&lt;/tt&gt; was put inside &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$3&lt;/tt&gt;, or removed from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use "&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;info watchpoints&lt;/tt&gt;" and "&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;delete &amp;lt;watchpointnum&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;" to manage
watchpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also regular breakpoints, which you set with "&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;b
FUNCNAME&lt;/tt&gt;".  It breaks whenever there is a call to a function that
happens to have the given name.  (It might be annoying to use for a
function like &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;__init__()&lt;/tt&gt; which has many homonyms.  There is no
support for breaking on a fully-qualified name or at a given line
number for now.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our demo, we stop at the line &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;x.value += 1&lt;/tt&gt;, which is where the
value was changed from 6 to 7.  Use &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;bcontinue&lt;/tt&gt; again to stop at the
line &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;lst1[50].value&lt;/span&gt; += 1&lt;/tt&gt;, which is where the value was changed from
5 to 6.  Now we know how this &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;value&lt;/tt&gt; attribute ends up being 7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
(19524)$ bcontinue
[searching 19427..19524]
[searching 19136..19427]

updating watchpoint value: $0.value =&amp;gt; 5
Reverse-hit watchpoint 1: $0.value
File "/tmp/x.py", line 7 in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;:
  import os

  class Foo(object):
      value = 5

  lst1 = [Foo() for i in range(100)]
&amp;gt; lst1[50].value += 1
  for x in lst1:
      x.value += 1

  for x in lst1:
      if x.value != 6:
...
(19422)$
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to use &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;bcontinue&lt;/tt&gt; yet another time.  It will stop now just before
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$0&lt;/tt&gt; is created.  At that point in time, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$0&lt;/tt&gt; refers to
an object that does not exist yet, so the watchpoint now evaluates to
an error message (but it continues to work as before, with that error
message as the string it currently evaluates to).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
(19422)$ bcontinue
[searching 19325..19422]

updating watchpoint value: $0.value =&amp;gt; RuntimeError:
               '$0' refers to an object created later in time
Reverse-hit watchpoint 1: $0.value
File "/tmp/x.py", line 6 in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;:
  import os

  class Foo(object):
      value = 5

&amp;gt; lst1 = [Foo() for i in range(100)]
  lst1[50].value += 1
  for x in lst1:
      x.value += 1

  for x in lst1:
...
(19371)$
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In big programs, the workflow is similar, just more complex.  Usually
it works this way: we find interesting points in time with some
combination of watchpoints and some direct commands to move around.
We write down on a piece of (real or virtual) paper these points in
history, including most importantly their time, so that we can
construct an ordered understanding of what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;revdb&lt;/tt&gt; can be annoying and sometimes even crash; but
the history you reconstruct can be kept.  All the times and
expressions printed are still valid when you restart &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;revdb&lt;/tt&gt;.  The
only thing "lost" is the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$NUM&lt;/tt&gt; objects, which you need to print
again.  (Maybe instead of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$0&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$1&lt;/tt&gt;, ...  we should use &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$&amp;lt;big
number&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, where the big number identifies uniquely the object by its
creation time.  These numbers would continue to be valid even after
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;revdb&lt;/tt&gt; is restarted.  They are more annoying to use than just
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$0&lt;/tt&gt; though.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Screencast:&lt;/b&gt; Here's a (slightly typo-y) screencast of cfbolz using the reverse debugger:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="current-issues"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Current issues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are using &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;revdb&lt;/tt&gt; on a log that took more than a few
minutes to record, then it can be painfully slow.  This is because
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;revdb&lt;/tt&gt; needs to replay again big parts of the log for some
operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pypy-revdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; is currently missing the following modules:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;thread&lt;/tt&gt; (implementing multithreading is possible, but not done
yet);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;cpyext&lt;/tt&gt; (the CPython C API compatibility layer);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;micronumpy&lt;/tt&gt; (minor issue only);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;_continuation&lt;/tt&gt; (for greenlets).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does not contain a JIT, and does not use our fast garbage
collectors.  You can expect &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pypy-revdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; to be maybe 3 times
slower than CPython.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only works on Linux and OS/X.  There is no fundamental reason for
this restriction, but it is some work to fix.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replaying a program uses a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more memory; maybe 15x as much than
during the recording.  This is because it creates many forks.  If
you have a program that consumes 10% of your RAM or more, you will
need to reduce &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;MAX_SUBPROCESSES&lt;/tt&gt; in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;process.py&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replaying also comes with a bunch of user interface issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Attempted to do I/O or access raw memory&lt;/tt&gt;: we get this whenever
trying to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;print&lt;/tt&gt; some expression that cannot be evaluated with
only the GC memory---or which can, but then the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;__repr__()&lt;/tt&gt;
method of the result cannot.  We need to reset the state with
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;bstep&lt;/tt&gt; + &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;step&lt;/tt&gt; before we can print anything else.  However,
if only the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;__repr__()&lt;/tt&gt; crashes, you still see the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$NUM =&lt;/tt&gt;
prefix, and you can use that &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;$NUM&lt;/tt&gt; afterwards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;id()&lt;/tt&gt; is globally unique, returning a reproducible 64-bit number,
so sometimes using &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;id(x)&lt;/tt&gt; is a workaround for when using &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;x&lt;/tt&gt;
doesn't work because of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Attempted to do I/O&lt;/tt&gt; issues (e.g.  &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;p
[id(x) for x in somelist]&lt;/tt&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as explained in the demo, next/bnext/finish/bfinish might jump
around a bit non-predictably.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;similarly, breaks on watchpoints can stop at apparently unexpected
places (when going backward, try to do "step" once).  The issue is
that it can only stop at the beginning of every line.  In the
extreme example, if a line is &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;foo(somelist.pop(getindex()))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;,
then &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;somelist&lt;/tt&gt; is modified in the middle.  Immediately before
this modification occurs, we are in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;getindex()&lt;/tt&gt;, and
immediately afterwards we are in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;foo()&lt;/tt&gt;.  The watchpoint will
stop the program at the end of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;getindex()&lt;/tt&gt; if running backward,
and at the start of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;foo()&lt;/tt&gt; if running forward, but never
actually on the line doing the change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;watchpoint expressions &lt;em&gt;must not&lt;/em&gt; have any side-effect at all.  If
they do, the replaying will get out of sync and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;revdb.py&lt;/tt&gt; will
complain about that.  Regular &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;p&lt;/tt&gt; expressions and statements can
have side-effects; these effects are discarded as soon as you move
in time again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sometimes even "&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;p import foo&lt;/tt&gt;" will fail with &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Attempted to do
I/O&lt;/tt&gt;.  Use instead "&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;p import sys; foo = &lt;span class="pre"&gt;sys.modules['foo']&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;help&lt;/tt&gt; to see all commands.  &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;backtrace&lt;/tt&gt; can be useful.
There is no &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;up&lt;/tt&gt; command; you have to move in time instead,
e.g. using &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;bfinish&lt;/tt&gt; to go back to the point where the current
function was called.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-revpdb-is-done"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How RevPDB is done&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to pick the main advantage of PyPy over CPython, it is that
we have got with the RPython translation toolchain a real place for
experimentation.  Every now and then, we build inside RPython some
feature that gives us an optionally tweaked version of the PyPy
interpreter---tweaked in a way that would be hard to do with CPython,
because it would require systematic changes everywhere.  The most
obvious and successful examples are the GC and the JIT.  But there
have been many other experiments along the same lines, from the
so-called &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/extradoc/-/blob/branch/default/tip/eu-report/D07.1_Massive_Parallelism_and_Translation_Aspects-2007-02-28.pdf"&gt;stackless transformation&lt;/a&gt; in the early days, to the STM
version of PyPy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RevPDB works in a similar way.  It is a version of PyPy in which some
operations are systematically replaced with other operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep the log file at a reasonable size, we duplicate the content of
all GC objects during replaying---by repeating the same actions on
them, without writing anything in the log file.  So that means that in
the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;pypy-revdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; binary, the operations that do arithmetic or
read/write GC-managed memory are not modified.  Most operations are
like that.  However, the other operations, the ones that involve
either non-GC memory or calls to external C functions, are tweaked.
Each of these operations is replaced with code that works in two
modes, based on a global flag:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in "recording" mode, we log the result of the operation (but not the
arguments);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in "replaying" mode, we don't really do the operation at all, but
instead just fetch the result from the log.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, all remaining unmodified operations (arithmetic and GC
load/store) are completely deterministic.  So during replaying, every
integer or non-GC pointer variable will have exactly the same value as
it had during recording.  Interestingly, it means that if the
recording process had a big array in non-GC memory, then in the
replaying process, the array is not allocated at all; it is just
represented by the same address, but there is nothing there.  When we
record "read item 123 from the array", we record the result of the
read (but not the "123").  When we replay, we're seeing again the same
"read item 123 from the array" operation.  At that point, we don't
read anything; we just return the result from the log.  Similarly,
when recording a "write" to the array, we record nothing (this write
operation has no result); so that when replaying, we redo nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note how that differs from anything managed by GC memory: GC objects
(including GC arrays) are really allocated, writes really occur, and
reads are redone.  We don't touch the log in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="other-reverse-debuggers-for-python"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other reverse debuggers for Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are already some Python experiments about &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debugger#Reverse_debugging"&gt;reverse debugging&lt;/a&gt;.
This is also known as "omniscient debugging".  However, I claim that
the result they get to is not very useful (for the purpose presented
here).  How they work is typically by recording changes to some
objects, like lists and dictionaries, in addition to recording the
history of where your program passed through.  However, the problem of
Python is that lists and dictionaries are not the end of the story.
There are many, many, many types of objects written in C which are
mutable---in fact, the immutable ones are the exception.  You can try
to systematically record all changes, but it is a huge task and easy
to forget a detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words it is a typical use case for tweaking the RPython
translation toolchain, rather than tweaking the CPython (or PyPy)
interpreter directly.  The result that we get here with RevPDB is more
similar to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rr-project.org/"&gt;rr&lt;/a&gt; anyway, in that only a relatively small number of
external events are recorded---not every single change to every single
list and dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;epdb: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/native-human/epdb"&gt;https://github.com/native-human/epdb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pode: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/rodsenra/pode"&gt;https://github.com/rodsenra/pode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For C:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rr: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rr-project.org/"&gt;https://rr-project.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;undodb-gdb: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://undo.io/"&gt;https://undo.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="future-work"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Future work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, it is alpha-level, and only works on Linux and OS/X.
So the plans for the immediate future are to fix the various
issues described above, and port to more operating systems.  The core of the system
is in the C file and headers in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;rpython/translator/revdb/src-revdb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For interested people, there is also the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/pypy/duhton/"&gt;Duhton&lt;/a&gt; interpreter and its
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;reverse-debugger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; branch, which is where I prototyped the RPython
concept before moving to PyPy.  The basics should work for any
interpreter written in RPython, but they require some specific code to
interface with the language; in the case of PyPy, it is in
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;pypy/interpreter/reverse_debugging.py&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In parallel, there are various user interface improvements that people
could be interested in, like a more "pdb++" experience.  (And the script
at &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;rpython/translator/revdb/revdb.py&lt;/tt&gt; should be moved out into some
more "official" place, and the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;reverse-debugger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; branch should be
merged back to default.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would certainly welcome any help!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-+- Armin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>revdb</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2016/07/reverse-debugging-for-python-8854823774141612670.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 11:39:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>