<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PyPy (Posts by hodgestar)</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.pypy.org/authors/hodgestar.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2026 &lt;a href="mailto:pypy-dev@pypy.org"&gt;The PyPy Team&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 00:22:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A new chapter for PyPy</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/08/a-new-chapter-for-pypy-8388322709667328389.html</link><dc:creator>hodgestar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;PyPy winds down its membership in the Software Freedom Conservancy&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Conservancy and PyPy's great work together&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pypy.org/"&gt;PyPy&lt;/a&gt; joined &lt;a href="https://sfconservancy.org/"&gt;Conservancy&lt;/a&gt; in
the &lt;a href="https://sfconservancy.org/blog/2011/jan/02/oct-dec-2010/"&gt;second half of 2010&lt;/a&gt;, shortly after the release of
PyPy 1.2, the first version to contain a fully functional JIT. &lt;a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/550427/"&gt;In 2013&lt;/a&gt;, PyPy
started supporting ARM, bringing its just-in-time speediness to many more devices and began working toward supporting NumPy to help
scientists crunch their numbers faster. Together, PyPy and Conservancy ran successful fundraising drives and facilitated payment
and oversight for &lt;a href="https://sfconservancy.org/blog/2016/dec/01/pypy-2016/"&gt;contractors and code sprints&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conservancy supported PyPy's impressive growth as it expanded support for
different hardware platforms, greatly improved the performance of C extensions,
and added support for Python 3 as the language itself evolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;The road ahead&lt;/h1&gt;
  
&lt;p&gt;Conservancy provides a fiscal and organizational home for projects that find the
freedoms and guardrails that come along with a charitable home advantageous for
their community goals. While this framework was a great fit for the early PyPy
community, times change and all good things must come to an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PyPy will remain a free and open source project, but the community's structure
and organizational underpinnings will be changing and the PyPy community will be
exploring options outside of the charitable realm for its next phase of growth
("charitable" in the legal sense -- PyPy will remain a community project).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the last year PyPy and Conservancy have worked together to properly
utilise the generous donations made by stalwart PyPy enthusiats over the years
and to wrap up PyPy's remaining charitable obligations. PyPy is grateful for
the Conservancy's help in shepherding the project toward its next chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Thank yous&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Conservancy: &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;"We are happy that Conservancy was able to help PyPy bring important software
for the public good during a critical time in its history. We wish the
community well and look forward to seeing it develop and succeed in new ways." &lt;br&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;— Karen Sandler, Conservancy's Executive Director&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From PyPy:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;"PyPy would like to thank Conservancy for their decade long support in
building the community and wishes Conservancy continued success in their
journey promoting, improving, developing and defending free and open source
sofware." &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p style="text-align: left;"&gt;— Simon Cross &amp;amp; Carl Friedrich Bolz-Tereick, on behalf of PyPy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;About&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://pypy.org/"&gt;PyPy&lt;/a&gt; is a multi-layer python interpreter with a built-in JIT compiler that runs
Python quickly across different computing environments.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://sfconservancy.org/"&gt;Software Freedom Conservancy&lt;/a&gt; (Conservancy) is a charity that provides a home
to over forty free and open source software projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pypy</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/08/a-new-chapter-for-pypy-8388322709667328389.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Leysin 2020 Sprint Report</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/03/leysin-2020-sprint-report-764567777353955897.html</link><dc:creator>hodgestar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;At the end of February ten of us gathered in Leysin, Switzerland to work on&lt;br&gt;
a variety of topics including &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/pyhandle/hpy/"&gt;HPy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://buildbot.pypy.org/summary?branch=py3.7"&gt;PyPy Python 3.7&lt;/a&gt; support and the PyPy&lt;br&gt;
migration to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/"&gt;Heptapod&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PIs_hVhn3RY/XnFDceuihNI/AAAAAAAAbRg/LKMOMWxeFw4jhcwqy8jx7iKzKE01fbfxQCEwYBhgL/s1600/2020_leysin_sprint_attendees.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="180" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PIs_hVhn3RY/XnFDceuihNI/AAAAAAAAbRg/LKMOMWxeFw4jhcwqy8jx7iKzKE01fbfxQCEwYBhgL/s320/2020_leysin_sprint_attendees.jpg" width="320"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
We had a fun and productive week. The snow was beautiful. There was skiing&lt;br&gt;
and lunch at the top of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berneuse"&gt;Berneuse&lt;/a&gt;, cooking together, some late nights at&lt;br&gt;
the pub next door, some even later nights coding, and of course the&lt;br&gt;
obligatory cheese fondue outing.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
There were a few of us participating in a PyPy sprint for the first time&lt;br&gt;
and a few familiar faces who had attended many sprints. Many different&lt;br&gt;
projects were represented including PyPy, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/pyhandle/hpy/"&gt;HPy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/graalvm/graalpython"&gt;GraalPython&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://foss.heptapod.net/pypy/"&gt;Heptapod&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/dgrunwald/rust-cpython"&gt;rust-cpython&lt;/a&gt;. The atmosphere was relaxed and welcoming, so if&lt;br&gt;
you're thinking of attending the next one -- please do!&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Topics worked on:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
HPy&lt;/h2&gt;
HPy is a new project to design and implement a better API for extending&lt;br&gt;
Python in C. If you're unfamiliar with it you can read more about it at&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/pyhandle/hpy/"&gt;HPy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
A lot of attention was devoted to the Big HPy Design Discussion which&lt;br&gt;
took up two full mornings. So much was decided that this will likely&lt;br&gt;
get its own detailed write-up, but bigger topics included:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the HPy GetAttr, SetAttr, GetItem and SetItem methods,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HPy_FromVoidP and HPy_AsVoidP for passing HPy handles to C functions&lt;br&gt;
that pass void* pointers to callbacks,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoiding having va_args as part of the ABI,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exception handling,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;support for creating custom types.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Quite a few things got worked on too:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;implemented support for writing methods that take keyword arguments with&lt;br&gt;
HPy_METH_KEYWORDS,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;implemented HPy_GetAttr, HPy_SetAttr, HPy_GetItem, and HPy_SetItem,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;started implementing support for adding custom types,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;started implementing dumping JSON objects in ultrajson-hpy,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;refactored the PyPy GIL to improve the interaction between HPy and&lt;br&gt;
PyPy's cpyext,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;experimented with adding HPy support to rust-cpython.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
And there was some discussion of the next steps of the HPy initiative&lt;br&gt;
including writing documentation, setting up websites and funding, and&lt;br&gt;
possibly organising another HPy gathering later in the year.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
PyPy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Georges gave a presentation on the Heptapod topic and branch workflows&lt;br&gt;
and showed everyone how to use hg-evolve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work was done on improving the PyPy CI buildbot post the move to&lt;br&gt;
heptapod, including a light-weight pre-merge CI and restricting&lt;br&gt;
when the full CI is run to only branch commits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of work was done improving the -D tests. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Armin demoed VRSketch and NaN Industries in VR, including an implementation&lt;br&gt;
of the Game of Life within NaN Industries!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skiing!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
Immediately after the sprint large parts of Europe and the world were&lt;br&gt;
hit by the COVID-19 epidemic. It was good to spend time together before&lt;br&gt;
travelling ceased to be a sensible idea and many gatherings were cancelled.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Keep safe out there everyone.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The HPy &amp;amp; PyPy Team &amp;amp; Friends&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;In joke for those who attended the sprint: Please don't replace this blog post&lt;br&gt;
with its Swedish translation (or indeed a translation to any other language :).&lt;/i&gt;</description><category>cpyext</category><category>CPython</category><category>GraalPython</category><category>Heptapod</category><category>hpy</category><category>pypy</category><category>pypy3</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2020/03/leysin-2020-sprint-report-764567777353955897.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2020 21:57:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>