<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PyPy (Posts by Samuele Pedroni)</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.pypy.org/authors/samuele-pedroni.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2026 &lt;a href="mailto:pypy-dev@pypy.org"&gt;The PyPy Team&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 00:22:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Planning a next release of PyPy</title><link>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2009/12/planning-next-release-of-pypy-4193252449406707091.html</link><dc:creator>Samuele Pedroni</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The PyPy core team is planning to make a new release before the next Pycon US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main target of the 1.2 release is packaging the good results
we have achieved applying our current JIT compiler generator to our
Python interpreter. Some of that progress &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pypy.org/posts/2009/10/gc-improvements-6174120095428192954.html"&gt;has been&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pypy.org/posts/2009/11/dusseldorf-sprint-report-2505348213879053352.html"&gt;chronicled in&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pypy.org/posts/2009/11/some-benchmarking-9211261260383281459.html"&gt;recent posts&lt;/a&gt; on the status blog. By releasing them in a
relatively stable prototype we want to encourage people to try them with their
own code and to gather feedback in this way. By construction the JIT compiler
should support all Python features, what may vary are the speedups
achieved (in some cases the JIT may produce worse results than the PyPy
interpreter which we would like to know) and the extra memory required
by it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the 1.2 release we will focus on the JIT stability first, less on
improving non-strictly JIT areas. The JIT should be good at many things
as shown by previous blog postings. We want the JIT compiler in the
release to work well on &lt;strong&gt;Intel 32 bits&lt;/strong&gt; on Linux, with Mac OS X and
Windows being secondary targets.  Which compilation targets work will
depend a bit on contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to finalize the release we intend to have a concentrated
effort ("virtual sprint") from the 22nd to the 29th of
January. Coordination will happen as usual through the #pypy irc
channel on freenode. Samuele Pedroni will take the role of release
manager as he already did in the past.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>release</category><guid>https://www.pypy.org/posts/2009/12/planning-next-release-of-pypy-4193252449406707091.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2009 14:55:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>